♪Confessing to the moon in the rustling wind back then♪
♪จันทร์เคยแจ่มกระจ่าง♪
♪Like a boat being swallowed up among the cities♪
♪พลันแปรเป็นทะเลคลั่ง♪
♪Watching the flowers fall in unease worries and troubles fill my mind♪
♪ตระหนกฟังเสียงบุปผาโรย♪
♪Am I going to where I want♪
♪ทุกที่ที่ไป♪
♪To stay or to leave you decide♪
♪ด้วยการไปหรืออยู่ของเจ้า♪
♪Nations are different♪
♪ปฐพีกับแผ่นดินก็ต่างกัน♪
♪One without desire is one that is not alive♪
♪ฟ้าดินไร้ใจ♪
♪Looking at the sky side by side♪
♪ร่วมเคียงชมนภา♪
♪We've gotten closer with time♪
♪กาลเข้มข้นกว่าเวลา♪
♪One glance the city of Chang'an is bare♪
♪มองผ่านปราดเดียว♪
♪Among the ridiculous people and things is me♪
♪ในเรื่องราวเหลวไหลของผู้คน♪
=Episode 46=
=ตอนที่ 46=
You pulled off a switcheroo.
หลี่เต๋ออวิ๋นตัวจริงตัวปลอม
It was a brilliant plan.
เป็นแผนชั้นเลิศจริง ๆ
You already had a plan to pull off at the Danfeng Gate.
ฝ่าบาททรงมีแผนหอตันเฟิ่งอยู่ก่อน
I merely added another precaution.
หม่อมฉันแค่ซ้อนแผนเท่านั้นเพคะ
Precisely speaking,
พูดให้ถูกก็คือ
I didn't come up with that plan
หอตันเฟิ่ง
on my own.
ไม่ใช่แผนของข้าคนเดียว
Brothers,
พี่น้องทั้งหลาย
tomorrow,
พรุ่งนี้
we'll seek an explanation from them!
พวกเราต้องการข้อสรุป
That's right!
ใช่
- We'll seek an explanation! - That's right.
- ต้องการข้อสรุป - ถูกต้อง
Let's go to Danfeng Gate!
พวกเราจะไปหอตันเฟิ่ง
- We'll head to Danfeng Gate! - That's right!
- ต้องไปหอตันเฟิ่ง - ใช่
Come! Bottoms up!
- มา - หมดจอก
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
can you hang in there?
ทนไหวหรือไม่เพคะ
I,
ข้า
even if I were to die,
ต่อให้ต้องตาย
I would die after I reach there.
ก็ต้องทนให้ถึงที่นั่นก่อนแล้วค่อยตาย
Very good.
ดีมากเพคะ
Did we miss anything out?
แล้วยังมีตรงไหนที่ขาดไปอีกหรือไม่เพคะ
We did.
มี
What is it?
อะไรเพคะ
How should I get out
ภายใต้การกักบริเวณเช่นนี้
when I'm placed under house arrest?
ข้าจะออกไปได้อย่างไร
You kept Gao Ping by your side for a long time.
ฝ่าบาททรงเก็บเกาผิงไว้นานขนาดนี้
Haven't you managed to bribe him yet?
ยังซื้อตัวเขาไม่สำเร็จอีกหรือเพคะ
How did you know
เจ้ารู้ได้อย่างไรว่าข้า
I kept him by my side on purpose?
ตั้งใจเก็บเขาเอาไว้
He acts so properly.
คนคนนี้ฉลาด
He knows everything he should,
อะไรที่ควรรู้ก็รู้ไปเสียหมด
but he doesn't know anything
อะไรที่ไม่ควรรู้
that he's not supposed to.
ก็ไม่รู้เรื่องเลยเช่นเดียวกัน
Gao Ping,
เกาผิง
go to my study room.
เจ้าไปที่ห้องหนังสือข้า
There's an item
ในลิ้นชักที่สามจากด้านซ้าย
within the third drawer on the left.
มีของบางอย่างอยู่
Go and retrieve it for me.
เจ้าไปหยิบมา
You can choose to give it to me or keep it for yourself.
จากนั้นก็เลือกว่า จะเอาให้ข้าหรือจะเก็บเอาไว้เอง
He has a younger sister.
เขามีน้องสาวคนหนึ่ง
They came from a poor family.
ที่บ้านยากจนตั้งแต่เล็ก
To not let him starve,
เพื่อไม่ให้เขาต้องอดตาย
his sister sold herself off as a slave.
น้องสาวจึงไปขายตัวเป็นบ่าว
He has no idea of her whereabouts.
ไม่รู้เป็นตายร้ายดีอย่างไร
(Chai,)
เสี่ยวไช
(you're still alive?)
เจ้ายังมีชีวิตอยู่หรือ
I've ordered my men
ข้าสั่งให้คน
to send Chai to Gao Ping's house.
ส่งตัวเสี่ยวไชไปที่บ้านเกาผิง
I asked him if he wanted to stamp his name on the page of history,
ถามเขาว่าอยากมีชื่อในประวัติศาสตร์
or to die within the palace
หรืออยากตายอยู่ในวังเงียบ ๆ
without anyone knowing his name.
ไม่มีใครกล่าวถึง
Seems like Eunuch Gao chose the first option.
แต่เกากงกงเลือกข้อแรก
I guess Han Ding
คิดว่าหานติ้ง
had told you everything.
ก็คงบอกเจ้าไปหมดแล้ว
But I didn't expect you to do this.
เพียงแต่ที่ข้าคิดไม่ถึงคือ
Why did you
ทำไมเจ้าถึง
bring the Violet Bureau back
พาคนของหน่วยอาภรณ์ม่วง
to assist me?
กลับมาช่วยเหลือได้
When they're fighting at Danfeng Gate,
คนแห่มาก่อเรื่องหน้าหอตันเฟิ่ง
as the Chancellor, Official Li Deyun
ใต้เท้าหลี่เต๋ออวิ๋นเป็นมหาเสนาบดี
will surely head to the gate and stop them.
ย่อมต้องออกมาคลี่คลายเหตุการณ์
This incident
เรื่องในครั้งนี้
is related to Official Li Deyun.
เกี่ยวข้องกับใต้เท้าหลี่เต๋ออวิ๋น
Qiu Ziliang
ฉิวจื่อเหลียง
wants to kill Official Li Deyun.
คิดลงมือต่อใต้เท้าหลี่เต๋ออวิ๋น
So, His Majesty must be
ดังนั้นจุดประสงค์ในครั้งนี้ของฝ่าบาท
trying to get rid of Qiu Ziliang.
คือต้องการกำจัดฉิวจื่อเหลียง
Cheng Ruoyu,
เฉิงรั่วอวี๋
once Official Li Deyun shows himself,
เมื่อถึงเวลาที่ใต้เท้าหลี่ออกหน้า
Qiu Ziliang
ทางด้านฉิวจื่อเหลียง
will surely act.
จะต้องมีความเคลื่อนไหวแน่
If a fight breaks out between them
หากเกิดเหตุไม่คาดฝันระหว่างความวุ่นวาย
Official Li's life might be in danger.
ชีวิตของใต้เท้าหลี่คงน่ากังวล
I have an idea.
ข้ามีแผน
It will protect Official Li Deyun.
รับรองว่าปลอดภัย
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
if I didn't find Han Ding back then,
ถ้าหม่อมฉันไม่ได้ไปหาหานติ้ง
were you planning
ฝ่าบาททรงตั้งใจ
to keep everything from me?
จะปิดเรื่องราวทุกอย่างกับหม่อมฉันใช่หรือไม่เพคะ
Lately,
ช่วงนี้หม่อมฉัน
I've been getting more and more confused.
รู้สึกสับสนมากจริง ๆ
I don't understand
หม่อมฉันไม่เข้าใจ
why Yanzhi saved me.
ว่าทำไมเยียนจือต้องช่วยหม่อมฉันด้วย
I don't know what secret she's keeping from me.
นางมีเจตนาอะไรแอบแฝงอยู่อีก
And I don't understand why
แล้วทำไมฝ่าบาท
Your Majesty would join hands with Yanzhi and Prince Guang.
ถึงได้ร่วมมือกับเยียนจือและอ๋องกวง
I thought Prince Guang was the third person?
อ๋องกวงก็คือมือที่สามไม่ใช่หรือเพคะ
You still can't reveal the truth to me,
หรือว่าทรงบอกหม่อมฉันไม่ได้
right?
ใช่หรือไม่เพคะ
I guess
คิดว่า
this is the time to tell you everything.
ตอนนี้คงถึงเวลาที่ต้องบอกเจ้าเสียที
Regarding this secret,
เรื่องนี้
besides me,
นอกจากข้าแล้ว
no one else knows about it.
บนโลกนี้ก็ไม่มีใครอีกที่รู้
Wang Yang's death
ว่าการตายของหวังหยาง
is one step in the Morning Dew Stratagem.
เป็นขั้นแรกของแผนเจาลู่
Ruoqing.
รั่วชิง
She's over there.
อยู่ตรงนั้นพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
The Morning Dew Stratagem was first proposed by Li Xu.
เดิมทีหลี่ซวี่เป็นคนเสนอแผนเจาลู่
Using the Morning Dew as an excuse,
โดยใช้ชื่อเจาลู่
they plan to slay Qiu Ziliang within a pavilion.
บีบฉิวจื่อเหลียงไปที่ศาลาแล้วลงมือสังหาร
But the late emperor was afraid that the plan might go awry.
แต่อดีตฮ่องเต้กลัวว่าแผนการจะล้มเหลว
He was afraid that Qiu Ziliang might seek revenge.
ถูกตามล้างแค้น
That's why the late emperor sacrificed his life
ดังนั้นอดีตฮ่องเต้จึงใช้ชีวิตเดิมพัน
to keep the bloodline of the Xing empire alive.
เก็บเชื้อเพลิงเอาไว้เพื่อต้าซิง
So, Your Majesty,
แล้วเชื้อเพลิงนั่น
you're the bloodline of the Xing empire.
ก็คือฝ่าบาท
The late emperor ordered me
อดีตฮ่องเต้สั่งให้ข้า
to endure necessary hardships to achieve our goal
นอนฟืนแข็งกินดีขมแบบโกวเจี้ยน
and ordered Wang Yang to act after he came up with a detailed plan.
สั่งให้หวังหยางดำเนินการตามแผน
He was my teacher.
หวังหยางก็เป็นอาจารย์ข้าเช่นกัน
For my sake,
เขาเองก็ยอม
he was involved in the plan.
เข้าร่วมแผนการนี้เพื่อข้า
We made a promise to each other.
พวกเราตกลงกันไว้แล้ว
Once the plan went awry,
ว่าทันทีที่แผนการล้มเหลว
we would spread the news of the posthumous edict
ก็จะปล่อยข่าวลือเรื่องพินัยกรรมออกไป
so that we could attract Qiu Ziliang's attention.
ดึงความสนใจของฉิวจื่อเหลียง
That's why
เพราะฉะนั้น
Han Yue went
หานเยว่ถึงได้เอาพินัยกรรม
to Teacher's residence with the posthumous edict.
ไปที่บ้านของอาจารย์
Teacher told me
อาจารย์บอกข้าว่า
that if we wanted Qiu Ziliang
ถ้าอยากให้ฉิวจื่อเหลียง
to trust me completely,
เชื่อข้าอย่างสุดใจ
I had to kill him personally
ก็ต้องลงมือฆ่าเขา
in front of Qiu Ziliang.
ต่อหน้าฉิวจื่อเหลียง
That's why...
ดังนั้น
That's why Qiu Ziliang and I
ดังนั้นข้ากับฉิวจื่อเหลียง
went to hunt you guys down.
จึงตามฆ่าพวกเจ้า
And
ส่วนฝ่าบาท
you brought special arrows with you.
ก็เอาลูกธนูที่สั่งทำเฉพาะดอกนั้นไป
Yes.
ใช่
But I didn't expect
แต่ข้าคิดไม่ถึงว่า
Qiu Ziliang to act before me.
ฉิวจื่อเหลียงจะลงมือฆ่าอาจารย์
He killed Teacher with an arrow.
ก่อนข้าไปหนึ่งก้าว
So, that's why Your Majesty
ดังนั้นฝ่าบาทจึงชิงลงมือ
shot me.
ฆ่าหม่อมฉันก่อนหนึ่งก้าว
That's how I was able to survive.
หม่อมฉันถึงได้มีชีวิตรอด
What about Yanzhi?
แล้วเยียนจือล่ะเพคะ
What's the story behind Yanzhi?
เกิดอะไรขึ้นกับเยียนจือ
What has she got to do
นางเกี่ยวข้องอะไร
with this incident?
กับเรื่องนี้ด้วย
Yanzhi was the descendant of a loyal official
เยียนจือเองก็เป็นทายาทของขุนนาง
who died in the Morning Dew Rebellion.
ในกบฏเจาลู่
She, I,
นางกับหม่อมฉัน
and Wu, the three of us are the same.
กับอาอู่ต่างก็เหมือน ๆ กัน
Yu'er.
อวี๋เอ๋อร์
Yanzhi...
เยียนจือ
- She... - Your Majesty!
- นาง - ฝ่าบาท
Your Majesty!
ฝ่าบาท
Something happened to Consort Shu.
พระสนมซูเฟยเกิดเรื่องแล้วพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
the Shencai Army and Chess of Generals Camp...
เช่นนั้นทัพเสินไฉกับสำนักหมากรุกล่ะพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
How is Yanzhi?
เยียนจือเป็นอย่างไรบ้าง
Her myocardium was damaged.
กล้ามเนื้อหัวใจบาดเจ็บ
She's fine for now.
กลับมาดีขึ้นได้ชั่วคราว
But her body is still weak.
แต่ก็ยังอ่อนแอมาก
Yu'er,
อวี๋เอ๋อร์
you should stay with her.
เจ้าอยู่เป็นเพื่อนนางหน่อย
I need to return to where I belong
ข้ายังต้องกลับไปที่ที่ข้าควรจะอยู่
and finish my part of the act.
เพื่อแสดงละครนี้ให้จบ
Yes, Your Highness.
พ่ะย่ะค่ะ
All of you may leave.
ออกไปให้หมด
Yes, sir.
เจ้าค่ะ
Yanzhi,
เยียนจือ
I've returned.
ข้ากลับมาแล้ว
Do you still remember?
ท่านยังจำได้หรือไม่
I once told you
ข้าเคยบอกท่านว่า
that there were many people
บนโลกนี้
I trusted in the world.
ข้ามีคนตั้งมากมายที่เชื่อใจได้
Qiu Yanzhi,
ฉิวเยียนจือ
have you
ท่านไม่เคย
never placed your trust in anyone else?
เชื่อใจใครมาก่อนเลยใช่หรือไม่
Even if your father is Duke Chu,
ต่อให้เป็นพ่อของท่าน ฉู่กั๋วกง
I don't think you would place your trust in him,
ท่านเองก็คงไม่เชื่อใจ
am I right?
ใช่หรือไม่
So what?
แล้วอย่างไรกัน
It's nothing.
ก็ไม่อย่างไร
I'm different from you.
ข้าไม่เหมือนกับท่าน
In this world,
บนโลกนี้
if people dare to tell me the truth,
มีคนมากมายขอเพียงกล้าพูด
I will place my trust in them.
ข้าก็จะเชื่อ
I'm sure
ตอนนั้น
you thought I was a fool, right?
ท่านต้องคิดว่าข้าโง่มาก ๆ เลยสินะ
But now, I wish to tell you this.
แต่ตอนนี้ข้าอยากบอกท่านว่า
You're someone I trust as well.
ท่านเองก็เป็นคนที่ข้าเชื่อใจ
Although I had placed my trust in the wrong person,
ถึงแม้แต่ก่อนข้าจะไว้ใจคนผิด
I had placed my trust in Aunt,
หลงเชื่อใจท่านอาหญิง
and...
แล้วก็
But this time,
แต่ครั้งนี้
I won't let anyone influence my decision.
ข้าจะไม่หลงเชื่อคำยั่วยุของใครอีก
I know it is right for me to trust you.
ข้าไม่เคยมองท่านผิดไป
Do you know something?
ท่านรู้หรือไม่
When I was at the Chess of Generals Camp,
ตอนที่อยู่ในสำนักหมากรุก
I saw many mechanisms within the camp.
ข้าเห็นกลไกตั้งมากมาย
But I felt that they were familiar to me.
แต่ข้ารู้สึกชินกับมันมากไป
It's because you forced me
เพราะว่าทุก ๆ กลไก
to solve every one of them
ท่านก็ล้วนบังคับข้าให้แก้ให้ได้
and you forced me to build them together with you.
คอยร่วมมือกับข้า
They saved me.
กลไกเหล่านั้นช่วยข้าเอาไว้
On that day,
วันนั้น
if one of the mechanisms
หากกลไกพวกนั้น
was fake
มีที่เป็นของปลอม
or didn't exist,
หรือไม่มีอยู่จริง
I would've been dead.
ข้าก็คงตายไปนานแล้ว
I was so relieved when I escaped the place.
ตอนที่ออกมาได้ข้ารู้สึกดีใจมาก
Because it proved that
เพราะนั่นยิ่งเป็นหลักฐานยืนยันได้ว่า
Qiu Ziliang
ฉิวจื่อเหลียง
was trying to drive a wedge between us.
อยากจะยุยงความสัมพันธ์ของพวกเรา
I know.
ข้ารู้
You didn't lie to me.
ว่าท่านไม่ได้หลอกข้า
Because if you did lie to me,
เพราะถ้าเป็นเช่นนั้นจริง
if you wanted to use me,
ท่านอยากใช้ประโยชน์จากข้า
or if you wanted to deceive me,
อยากหลอกข้าละก็
why would you
ท่านจะเอาเสื้อเกราะของท่าน
disarm yourself in front of me?
มาให้ข้าทำไมกัน
But I don't understand one thing.
เพียงแต่ข้าไม่เข้าใจ
Why must Qiu Ziliang
ว่าทำไมฉิวจื่อเหลียง
force me to hate you?
ต้องบีบข้าให้เกลียดท่านด้วย
Aunt even used her death to set you up.
ท่านอาหญิงถึงกับยอมตายเพื่อใส่ร้ายท่าน
And Prince Guang and His Majesty,
แล้วสิ่งที่ท่านอ๋องกวงกับฝ่าบาท
they still won't tell me what's going on.
ไม่ยอมพูดออกมานั้น
Why are they doing so?
มันเป็นเพราะอะไรกันแน่
Yanzhi,
เยียนจือ
please wake up,
ท่านรีบฟื้นขึ้นมาเถอะ
okay?
ได้หรือไม่
Wake up and teach me, just like how you did in the past.
มาสั่งสอนข้าเหมือนแต่ก่อน
Yanzhi.
เยียนจือ
You're awake?
ท่านฟื้นแล้ว
I'm sorry.
ข้าขอโทษ
Enough.
เอาละ ๆ
Let's stop crying.
พวกเราไม่ต้องร้องแล้ว
We still need to join hands
พวกเรายังต้องร่วมมือกัน
to defeat the eunuch's faction.
สู้กับขันทีอีกนะ
Look.
ท่านดูสิ
I'm doing fine, right?
ข้าก็ยังสบายดีอยู่ไม่ใช่หรืออย่างไรกัน
Both of us are doing fine.
พวกเราต่างก็สบายดีอยู่
Let's stop crying.
ไม่ร้องแล้วนะ
- Let's stop crying. - No.
- ไม่ร้องแล้ว - ไม่ได้
Ruoling,
รั่วหลิง
you must leave.
ไป
This is too dangerous.
อันตรายเกินไป
Heng'an is too dangerous.
เหิงอันอันตรายเกินไป
All the more I need to stay here.
เช่นนั้นข้าก็ยิ่งต้องอยู่ที่เหิงอันต่อ
Listen to me.
เจ้าฟังที่ข้าพูดนะ
Go and find Yan Xiu.
เจ้าไปหาเหยียนซิว
Yan Xiu promised me
เหยียนซิวเคยรับปากข้า
that he would protect you with his life.
ว่าจะใช้ชีวิตคุ้มครองเจ้าให้ปลอดภัย
Go and find him.
เจ้าไปหาเขา
Both of you should leave Heng'an immediately.
พวกเจ้ารีบออกไปจากเหิงอัน
You're hiding something from me, am I right?
ท่านมีเรื่องปิดบังข้าจริง ๆ ใช่หรือไม่
What is
เหตุผลที่พิเศษนั่น
the special reason behind all of this?
คืออะไรกันแน่
What is the reason
เหตุผลที่ทำให้ท่าน
you're risking your life
เสี่ยงชีวิตปกป้องข้า ช่วยชีวิตข้า
to protect, save, and assist me?
ช่วยเหลือข้าคืออะไรกันแน่
You know how stubborn I am
นิสัยดื้อรั้นที่ต้องการตามหา
when I try
คำตอบของข้า
to seek answers.
ท่านก็รู้ดี
If you don't tell me the truth,
หากท่านไม่บอกข้า
I will continue investigating,
ข้าก็จะสืบต่อไป
until I find out the truth.
สืบจนกว่าข้าจะได้รู้ความจริง
Yanzhi.
เยียนจือ
Fine.
ได้
I'll tell you.
ข้าจะพูด
But this isn't the time.
แต่ไม่ใช่ตอนนี้
Tomorrow.
รอให้ถึงพรุ่งนี้
If both of us are still alive by tomorrow,
หากพรุ่งนี้เจ้ากับข้ายังมีชีวิตอยู่
I'll tell you everything.
ข้าก็จะบอกทุกอย่างกับเจ้า
Why must we wait until tomorrow?
ทำไมถึงต้องเป็นพรุ่งนี้
Because someone is going
เพราะว่ามีคนผู้หนึ่ง
to reach Heng'an by tomorrow.
จะมาถึงเหิงอันในวันพรุ่งนี้
Nine.
เสี่ยวจิ่วจื่อ
Nine, wake up.
เจ้าฟื้นสิ เสี่ยวจิ่วจื่อ
Wake up.
ฟื้นสิ
Nine.
เสี่ยวจิ่วจื่อ
What's wrong?
เจ้าเป็นอะไรไป
Even you...
แม้แต่เจ้า
Even a bird is leaving me.
ก็ไปจากข้าไปเหมือนกันหรือ
Was it because I lost my military authority?
เจ้าคิดว่าอำนาจทางทหารของข้าถูกแย่งไป
You're betraying me as well?
เจ้าก็ล้มลงไปด้วยหรือ
Have all of you betrayed me?
พวกเจ้าก็พังทลายลงไปด้วยหรือ
Fine.
ดี
Qi Yan.
ฉีเยี่ยนเอ๋ย
Good.
ดี
Very good.
ดีมาก
Left Chariot.
จั่วเชอ
Yes, sir.
ขอรับ
You,
เจ้าไป
go and kill Zhang Zhongru
เจ้าไปฆ่า
and
ตาเฒ่า
the other old fools.
จางจงหรูนั่นซะ
Bring their heads to me.
เอาหัวของพวกมันมาหาข้า
Then you'll become the Chess Overseer!
แล้วเจ้าจะได้เป็นผู้นำสำนักหมากรุก
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
it's getting cold outside.
อากาศเย็นแล้ว
You should return to your room and rest.
กลับไปพักผ่อนเถอะเพคะ
Many years ago,
หลายปีก่อน
during the night before the Morning Dew Rebellion,
หนึ่งคืนก่อนกบฏเจาลู่
it was raining cats and dogs outside.
มีฝนตกหนัก
My brother
เสด็จพี่
watched the rain by himself
ก็ยืนมองฝน
at this very same spot.
อยู่คนเดียวเช่นนี้เหมือนกัน
I was looking at him from a distance.
ข้ามองเขาอยู่ในที่อันห่างไกล
I didn't dare to approach him,
ข้าไม่กล้าเข้าใกล้
and I couldn't approach him.
แล้วก็เข้าใกล้ไม่ได้ด้วย
Back then, I was wondering
ตอนนั้นข้าคิดว่า
what my brother was thinking about.
เสด็จพี่กำลังดำริอะไรอยู่กันแน่
I guess the late emperor
สิ่งที่อดีตฮ่องเต้ดำริในตอนนั้น
was thinking of the same thing as you, Your Majesty.
ก็คงจะเหมือนฝ่าบาทในตอนนี้เพคะ
But to me,
แต่ที่ข้าคิดก็คือ
I am much luckier than my brother.
ข้าโชคดีกว่าเสด็จพี่มากนัก
Zheng Lu and Li Xu,
เจิ้งลู่ หลี่ซวี่
both of them are mediocre officials.
ล้วนเป็นพวกคนธรรมดาทั่วไป
But I have
แต่ข้างกายของข้า
Teacher,
มีอาจารย์
Li Deyun,
มีหลี่เต๋ออวิ๋น
and you by my side.
และยังมีเจ้าอยู่
♪Are there any colorful and weird forms♪
♪แสงสีแปลกประหลาดบ้างหรือไม่♪
♪The sun, moon, and stars are within reach♪
♪อาทิตย์จันทราดาราแขวนไว้ที่ปลายหู♪
♪If time didn't stop♪
♪หากมิใช่เวลาหยุดนิ่งในสายลม♪
The customs are rich.
ธรรมเนียมกาลรากฐานแน่น
The emperor is kind and amicable.
จ้าวแว่นแคว้นปรีชาชาญ
Walking while humming a tune,
เฟื่องฟูศิลปาการ
people live in peace.
สันติผ่านทั่วภพแดน
♪I thought they were tears♪
♪ใช้เงาของข้าบดบังเจ้า♪
♪Letting my heart sing a low tune♪
♪ให้เสียงหัวใจพร่ำเพลงรักเพียงแผ่วเบา♪
Yu'er,
อวี๋เอ๋อร์
one day,
จะต้องมีสักวัน
I will return you
ข้าจะคืนความสงบสุข
and the civilians
ให้กับเจ้า
a peaceful world.
ให้กับแผ่นดิน
I trust you, Your Majesty.
หม่อมฉันเชื่อเพคะ
♪Because of constant pursuit♪
♪คลาดกันชั่วฟ้าดินสลาย♪
♪Countless ties within the vast world♪
♪บนโลกผูกพันเพียงไร♪
♪Worrying about the troubles in our mind, just to find a companion♪
♪คนเขลาเป็นทุกข์เพื่อการครองคู่♪
So, are you willing
เช่นนั้นเจ้ายินยอม
to stay by my side
ร่วมผ่าน
and embrace a prosperous world together?
ความรุ่งโรจน์ข้างข้าหรือไม่
♪No matter how wide the world is♪
♪ต่อให้ฟ้าดินกว้างไพศาล ก็ไม่เพียงพอต่อทะเลใจ♪
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาทเพคะ
don't forget.
พระองค์ทรงอย่าลืม
I'm your Sword Bearer.
หม่อมฉันคือผู้ถือกระบี่ของพระองค์นะเพคะ
♪Disregard my pride♪
♪ละทิ้งแผ่นดิน ละทิ้งท่วงท่า♪
♪True love without prosperity♪
♪ความจริงใจที่ไม่วิจิตรก็แสนเอ็นดู♪
Both of us
พวกเราสองคน
are destined to be together forever.
ถูกลิขิตให้อยู่ด้วยกันตลอดไป
This is our fate.
นี่เป็นลิขิตสวรรค์
♪The light that's about to get extinguished♪
♪โคมที่มอดดับอยู่เคียงคู่ท่ามกลางอากาศอบอุ่น♪
♪Don't mind the long sigh of worry♪
♪อย่าให้ความกังวลทอดถอนยาวนาน♪
It is fate indeed.
ก็เป็นลิขิตสวรรค์
♪Let us finish speaking of our love in this lifetime♪
♪ให้เราได้พูดคำว่ารักนี้ไปจนนิรันดร์♪
Fate was the one
เป็นลิขิตสวรรค์
♪Dream will fulfil your insomnia♪
♪พะวงยากข่มตามีห้วงฝันมาคลี่คลาย♪
that sent you to my side.
ที่ส่งเจ้ามาอยู่ข้างกายข้า
Fate was the one that led both of us
แล้วก็เป็นลิขิตสวรรค์ให้เจ้ากับข้าสองคน
to stay together forever
ฝ่าฟันอุปสรรคมากมาย
even after all that we had been through.
ไม่แยกจากกัน
♪We shouldn't waste time♪
♪ก็อย่าเสียเวลาไปต่อกรกับโชคชะตา♪
♪A hug contains infinite longing♪
♪โอบกอดยิ่งยากความคิดถึงก็ยิ่งเติมเต็ม♪
♪Promises made, though life is short♪
♪ชีวิตยิ่งสั้นสัญญาก็ยังคงอยู่นับพันปี♪
♪Love will never deteriorate♪
♪ความรักยากผุพังขอเพียงข้ายังอยู่♪
♪The sun and moon will never fall♪
♪อาทิตย์จันทราไม่มีทางร่วงหล่น♪
♪Our azure dream, disrupted♪
♪พัวพันโลกแห่งความฝันของสองเรา♪
♪Do not let the long sigh of the heavens♪
♪อย่าให้ความกังวลทอดถอนยาวนาน♪
♪Finish our lovers' prattle♪
♪ให้เราได้พูดคำว่ารักนี้ไปจนนิรันดร์♪
For tonight's operation,
ปฏิบัติการในคืนนี้
we must succeed
จะต้องสำเร็จเท่านั้น
without failure!
ห้ามล้มเหลวเด็ดขาด
Yes, sir!
ขอรับ
Depart!
ออกเดินทาง
Who's there?
ใครน่ะ
So, it has begun.
เริ่มแล้ว
His Majesty has begun to act.
ฝ่าบาทเริ่มแล้ว
Your Highness, what about you?
เช่นนั้นท่านอ๋องล่ะพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Some things
มีบางเรื่อง
will present themselves to you.
ที่มาอยู่ต่อหน้าเอง
And you can't afford to reject them.
ท่านไม่อาจปฏิเสธมันได้
Your Highness, you should make up your mind earlier.
ท่านอ๋องรีบตัดสินใจเถอะ
I lack one item.
ยังขาดของอีกหนึ่งอย่าง
One key item.
ที่สำคัญที่สุดเช่นกัน
Sir,
ใต้เท้า
I've brought Zhang Zhongru's head with me.
ข้าได้หัวของจางจงหรูมาแล้วขอรับ
now,
ตอนนี้
can I become the official Chess Overseer?
ข้าเป็นผู้นำสำนักหมากรุกแล้วใช่หรือไม่ขอรับ
Sure.
ใช่
Thank you, sir.
ขอบคุณใต้เท้า
♪The golden dagger-axe releases the sunny sky♪
♪วางศาสตรามองฟ้าคราม ขอเกียจคร้านครึ่งวันไม่ทำใด♪
♪The black and white mirror is hazy♪
♪ดำขาวเพียงมองมัวตา สุขทุกข์หนึ่งราตรีผัน♪
♪Seal old scores♪
♪เก็บหนี้แค้นลงหีบปิดฝัง วันพรุ่งอย่าได้เร่งทุรน♪
♪The voice was low and close yesterday♪
♪เสียงแว่ววันวานแผ่วเบา ทัพเดียวดายยังยากกลบทำนอง♪
♪Why is fate secretly torturing me?♪
♪ชะตาไยเคี่ยวกรำจนช้ำตรม ทว่าคงรู้จักรักหยกถนอมบุปผา♪
♪There are too many trivial times in this world♪
♪ปุถุชนยากหลุดพ้นพันธะ รักและชังทำร้ายคนจนปลาในสระ♪
♪And the duckweed on the water♪
♪ซึ่งจอกแหนที่ผุดเกิดขึ้นมา แสดงถึงใจข้าอย่างชัดเจน♪
♪To me life and death♪
♪ความเป็นตายสำหรับข้า ดั่งเล็งธนูใส่หมอกควัน♪
♪Not in a hurry to disperse the wind♪
♪ไม่รีบเร่งเป่าพัดลมสลาย ขอเข้าสู่ฝันท่านก่อน♪
♪This small worldly affair♪
♪ฝุ่นธุลีเล็ก ๆ น้อย ๆ แม้ด้อยค่าบนโลกา♪
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
it's time to attend the imperial court meeting.
ต้องเข้าประชุมเช้าแล้วพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Change my attire for me.
เปลี่ยนเสื้อให้ข้าที
♪The wind cuts a red thread♪
♪พายุกรีดผ่านแดงฉาน สีชาดตัดกลางหนึ่งลมคลั่ง♪
♪You don't realize the deep feelings♪
♪เจ้าชีวิตไม่ประจักษ์ไมตรีลึก รักกลับจารึกห้วงฝันข้า♪
Qi Yan,
ฉีเยี่ยนเอ๋ย ฉีเยี่ยน
you took my military authority yesterday,
เมื่อวานแย่งอำนาจทางทหารของข้าไป
and now, you want to restore the imperial court meeting?
วันนี้ก็คิดจะออกว่าราชกิจตอนเช้า
Have you arranged everything?
เจ้าจัดการเรียบร้อยแล้วใช่หรือไม่
Sir,
เรียนใต้เท้า
the Shencai Army is ready.
ระดมทัพเสินไฉเสร็จแล้วขอรับ
We are at your command.
รอคำสั่งใต้เท้าขอรับ
Good.
ดี
Now, I will show you
ข้าก็จะสอนเจ้า
how a imperial court meeting
ว่าอะไรคือ
looks like!
การว่าราชกิจตอนเช้า
His Majesty has arrived!
ฝ่าบาทเสด็จแล้ว
Long live Your Majesty.
ทรงพระเจริญหมื่นปี หมื่นปี หมื่น ๆ ปี
All of you may rise.
ลุกขึ้นเถอะ
Thank you, Your Majesty.
ขอบพระทัยฝ่าบาท
Where are the rest?
ทำไมมีคนหายไปเยอะเช่นนี้
Where's General Zhang?
แม่ทัพจางล่ะ
Duke Chu has arrived.
ฉู่กั๋วกงมาถึงแล้ว
- Duke Chu.
ฉู่กั๋วกง ๆ
Your Majesty, who else do you wish to see?
ฝ่าบาทยังอยากจะพบใครอีกหรือพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Official Qiu,
ใต้เท้าฉิว
I remember
เหมือนข้าจำได้ว่า
that I've issued an edict
มีราชโองการ
for you to stay at home and reflect upon your actions.
ให้ท่านสำนึกตนรอคำสั่งอยู่ที่บ้านมิใช่หรือ
Your Majesty, you did issue that edict before.
ฝ่าบาทเคยตรัสไว้จริง ๆ
But last night,
แต่เมื่อคืนกระหม่อมได้ยินว่า
I heard that many generals were slain
ในเมืองเหิงอัน
within Heng'an City.
มีแม่ทัพตายไปไม่น้อย
Your Majesty, I was worried for your safety.
กระหม่อมเป็นห่วงความปลอดภัยของฝ่าบาท
That's why I'm here to protect you.
จึงได้รีบรุดมาอารักขาฝ่าบาทโดยเฉพาะ
There is chaos within Heng'an City.
ในเมืองเหิงอันไม่ค่อยสงบสุข
General Zhang
แม่ทัพจางผู้นี้
ended up dead.
บทจะตายก็ตาย
Officials,
ใต้เท้าทุกท่าน
all of you must be careful.
พวกท่านต้องระวังนะ
Yu'er.
อวี๋เอ๋อร์
Yes, Your Majesty.
เพคะ
Keep General Zhang's head safe.
เก็บหัวของแม่ทัพจาง
Enshrine his head.
ใส่โลงเอาไว้ให้ดี
Yes, Your Majesty.
เพคะ
Wait.
ช้าก่อน
Do you think you have the right to touch his head?
หัวนี้จะให้เจ้าแตะต้องได้อย่างไร
Royal retainers from Zhenwu have arrived!
ขุนนางเมืองเจิ้นอู๋ขอเข้าเฝ้า
Greetings, Your Majesty.
ถวายบังคมฝ่าบาท
Long live Your Majesty.
ขอทรงพระเจริญหมื่นปี หมื่นปี หมื่น ๆ ปี
You may rise.
ลุกขึ้นเถอะ
Thank you, Your Majesty.
ขอบพระทัยฝ่าบาท
(Princess Misha?)
(ท่านหญิงหมีซา)
Your Majesty,
ได้ข่าวว่าวันที่สองเดือนหน้า
I heard that your birthday is on the 2nd of next lunar month.
ก็จะเป็นวันพระบรมราชสมภพของฝ่าบาท
Under General Liu's order,
หม่อมฉันได้รับคำสั่งจากแม่ทัพหลิว
I'm here to offer our tributes.
ให้มาถวายของกำนัลเพคะ
This is Zhenwu's Golden Horse Seal.
นี่เป็นตราอาชาทองเจิ้นอู๋
With that seal, you have 80,000 elite soldiers under your command.
ที่สามารถระดมกองทัพแปดหมื่นนายได้ทุกเมื่อ
Your Majesty, they're under your command now.
แล้วแต่ฝ่าบาทจะบัญชา
Princess Misha?
ท่านหญิงหมีซาหรือ
How are you not dead yet?
เหตุใดเจ้ายังไม่ตายอีกล่ะ
Yes.
นั่นสิ
Duke Chu,
ฉู่กั๋วกง
I'm sure you didn't expect this.
คิดไม่ถึงใช่หรือไม่
I'm still alive.
ว่าข้ายังไม่ตาย
You've imprisoned me
เจ้าพยายามจะกักขังข้าไว้หลายหน
and hunted me down numerous times.
ตามจับข้า
His Majesty found a replacement
ฝ่าบาททรงหาคน
who looked just like me
ที่หน้าตาเหมือนข้า
to die on behalf of me.
ให้มาตายแทนข้า
That's how I was able to escape
ข้าถึงได้หนีรอดมาได้
and return to my state.
ได้กลับบ้าน
My face
ใบหน้าของข้านี้
was disfigured because of your lackey,
ก็ถูกจั่วเชอสุนัขรับใช้ของเจ้า
the Left Chariot.
ทำจนเป็นเช่นนี้
Today.
วันนี้
Today, I'm here
วันนี้ข้ามาที่นี่
to seek an explanation from you.
ก็เพื่อจะมาทวงความยุติธรรมจากเจ้า
All thanks to Duke Chu,
ขอบคุณฉู่กั๋วกงที่ช่วยเหลือ
the people of Zhenwu
เจิ้นอู๋ถึงได้
are loyal to me.
ภักดีต่อข้าเช่นนี้
The Zhenwu Army isn't in Heng'an.
ทัพเจิ้นอู๋ไม่ได้อยู่ที่เหิงอันสักหน่อย
What can you do to me?
จะทำอะไรข้าได้
How do you know the Zhenwu Army isn't in Heng'an?
ท่านรู้ได้อย่างไรว่าไม่อยู่ที่เหิงอัน
Since I'm here,
ในเมื่อข้ามาแล้ว
naturally,
กองทัพ
my army is here as well.
แน่นอนว่าต้องมาได้
Duke Chu, if you don't believe me,
หากฉู่กั๋วกงไม่เชื่อ
you may take a look outside.
สามารถออกไปดูที่นอกตำหนักเองได้
Duke Chu,
ฉู่กั๋วกง
besides killing people without any restraint,
นอกจากสังหารคนตามอำเภอใจ
you haven't noticed
กลับไม่เคยสนใจ
the situation outside the gate, am I right?
นอกประตูเมืองเลยหรือ
All of you!
พวกเจ้า
Useless fools.
เศษสวะ
What's the point of keeping you guys alive?
เลี้ยงพวกเจ้าไว้มีประโยชน์อะไร
Such audacity.
บังอาจ
How dare you be rampant
อยู่ในท้องพระโรง
within the imperial court?
จะให้ท่านอาละวาดเช่นนี้ได้อย่างไร
Rampant?
อาละวาดหรือ
I've always been like this.
กระหม่อมก็เป็นเช่นนี้มาตลอด
Your Majesty, don't tell me you don't know about that?
หรือฝ่าบาทมิทรงทราบอย่างนั้นหรือ
If I can kill General Zhang,
กระหม่อมสามารถสังหารแม่ทัพจาง
General Ma, and General Wang,
แม่ทัพหม่า แม่ทัพหวังได้
that means I can kill you at any time.
กระหม่อมจะแตะต้องพระองค์เมื่อไรก็ได้เช่นกัน
Official Qiu,
ใต้เท้าฉิว
are you sure
ท่านมั่นใจหรือ
you killed the real General Zhang?
ว่าที่ท่านสังหารไปเป็นแม่ทัพจาง
Maybe there's something wrong with Left Chariot's eyes.
ข้าเกรงว่าสายตาของจั่วเชอจะไม่ดี
What if he killed the wrong person again?
แล้วฆ่าคนผิดอีกจะทำเช่นไร
Someone!
ตามคนมา
Where are the generals of the Shencai Army?
แม่ทัพทัพเสินไฉอยู่ที่ใด
Let go of me!
ปล่อยข้านะ
Hurry up!
รีบไป
Go!
ไป ๆ
Don't try anything funny! Hurry!
อย่าขัดขืน เร็ว
- Don't try anything funny! - Kneel!
อยู่นิ่ง ๆ คุกเข่าลง ๆ
(Brave and Heroic)
(ชาญชัย)
Under His Majesty's order,
ได้รับพระบัญชาจากฝ่าบาท
we are to eradicate the rebels within Shencai Army.
ให้กำจัดกบฏในทัพเสินไฉ
Those who resist
ผู้ขัดขืน
will be executed!
ฆ่าโดยไม่ละเว้น
Qi Yan,
ฉีเยี่ยน
good job.
เจ้าเก่งมาก
Do you think
เจ้าคิดว่า
you can win against me?
จะชนะข้าได้อย่างนั้นหรือ
I told you before.
ข้าเคยบอกแล้ว
I will surely win.
ว่าข้าจะต้องชนะ
You're wrong.
เจ้าผิดแล้ว
As long as I'm around,
ขอเพียงข้ายังอยู่
you'll never be able to win against me.
เจ้าก็ไม่มีทางชนะได้หรอก
Do you think you can win
อาศัยแค่
with Little Fish?
ปลาน้อยหรือ
with these useless fools
กลุ่มคนไร้ความสามารถ
within and outside the imperial court?
ในราชสำนักพวกนี้หรือ
You won't be able to touch me.
เจ้าแตะต้องข้าไม่ได้หรอก
Try me if you dare.
ไม่เชื่อเจ้าก็ลองดูสิ
Princess Misha,
ท่านหญิงหมีซา
you're a tough girl indeed.
เจ้านี่ตายยากเสียจริง
You've been dead time and time again.
ตายไปครั้งแล้วครั้งเล่า
Yet, somehow, you're still alive.
ก็ยังไม่ตายสักที
You're a great girl.
เจ้าเก่งมากจริง ๆ
Seems like
ดูเหมือนว่า
you'll be the empress.
ตำแหน่งฮองเฮาจะต้องเป็นของเจ้าแน่แล้ว
Stop right there!
หยุดนะ
Kill him!
ฆ่า
Stop running!
อย่าหนีนะ
After him!
ตามไป
Stop right there!
หยุดนะ
Capture him!
จับเขาไว้
Stop running!
อย่าหนี
Kill them!
ฆ่า ๆ
Close the palace gate!
ปิดประตูวัง
Kill all of them!
ฆ่าทิ้งซะ
♪Life is a dream how long do happy times last♪
♪ชีวิตล่องลอยดุจฝัน เคยสุขกี่ครั้ง♪
♪The sword can't break this karma♪
♪ชักดาบฟันฟาด กลับมิอาจสะบั้นเหตุและผล♪
♪Look how blurry and lonely the world is♪
♪มองฟ้ามองดินล้วนไม่ยินไม่แยแส♪
♪Still can't let go of this life as time goes by♪
♪ตะวันรุ่งจันทราโรย ชีพนี้ยังคงน่าถนอม♪
♪Even the iron and golden dagger-axe cannot extinguish the fire in my heart♪
♪ควบอาชาพร้อมอาวุธ มิอาจหยุดไฟในทรวง♪
♪Remembering the past and letting time while away♪
♪คิดถึงฝันในวันเก่า นานเท่านาน ยังคงเจ็บ♪
♪The past is in front of you♪
♪อดีตพลันไหลผ่านสองตา♪
♪Forgetting while piecing it together♪
♪ทางหนึ่งเพียรลืม อีกทางเพียรจำ♪
♪Like when I sincerely put my hands together♪
♪หากข้าประกบมือประนมกร♪
♪I only wish that you can be saved♪
♪ไหว้วอนให้เจ้าได้หลุดพ้น♪
♪The past is in front of you♪
♪อดีตพลันไหลผ่านสองตา♪
♪Forgetting while piecing it together♪
♪ทางหนึ่งเพียรลืม อีกทางเพียรจำ♪
♪Like when I sincerely put my hands together♪
♪หากข้าประกบมือประนมกร♪
♪I only wish that you can be saved♪
♪ไหว้วอนให้เจ้าได้หลุดพ้น♪